<?xml version="1.0" encoding="utf-8"?>
<feed xmlns="http://www.w3.org/2005/Atom" xmlns:media="http://search.yahoo.com/mrss/">
    <title>Atlancia</title>
    <link href="https://atlancia.com/feed.xml" rel="self" />
    <link href="https://atlancia.com" />
    <updated>2025-08-08T09:38:27-04:00</updated>
    <author>
        <name>Liam Shaw</name>
    </author>
    <id>https://atlancia.com</id>

    <entry>
        <title>Leading from the Middle - How Direct Leaders can Shape Innovation Culture</title>
        <author>
            <name>Liam Shaw</name>
        </author>
        <link href="https://atlancia.com/leading-from-the-middle-how-direct-leaders-can-shape-innovation-culture.html"/>
        <id>https://atlancia.com/leading-from-the-middle-how-direct-leaders-can-shape-innovation-culture.html</id>
        <media:content url="https://atlancia.com/media/posts/5/middle-header.webp" medium="image" />

        <updated>2025-02-17T00:00:00-05:00</updated>
            <summary>
                <![CDATA[
                        <img src="https://atlancia.com/media/posts/5/middle-header.webp" alt="" />
                    In the sclerosis of corporate hierarchies, middle management often finds itself caricatured as a relic of bygone organizational structures, scar tissue left behind by the Peter Principle. From the bumbling inefficiency of Office Space’s Lumbergh to the clichéd “paper-pusher,” middle managers have been the subject&hellip;
                ]]>
            </summary>
        <content type="html">
            <![CDATA[
                    <p><img src="https://atlancia.com/media/posts/5/middle-header.webp" class="type:primaryImage" alt="" /></p>
                <p id="4b21" class="pw-post-body-paragraph mg mh ha mi b mj mk ml mm mn mo mp mq mr ms mt mu mv mw mx my mz na nb nc nd gp bk" data-selectable-paragraph="">In the sclerosis of corporate hierarchies, middle management often finds itself caricatured as a relic of bygone organizational structures, scar tissue left behind by the Peter Principle. From the bumbling inefficiency of <em class="ne">Office Space</em>’s Lumbergh to the clichéd “paper-pusher,” middle managers have been the subject of fascination, frustration, and ridicule. But these stereotypes belie a deeper truth: middle managers, especially in knowledge work are essential stewards of an organizations most important and undervalued resource: the team.</p>
<p id="ed5d" class="pw-post-body-paragraph mg mh ha mi b mj mk ml mm mn mo mp mq mr ms mt mu mv mw mx my mz na nb nc nd gp bk" data-selectable-paragraph="">From my experience as an Agile coach, I have seen firsthand how strong middle management can transform teams. When managers embrace a servant-leadership mindset — prioritizing the needs of their teams over the impulse to dictate outcomes — their teams flourish. Psychological safety increases, innovation thrives, and organizations become more resilient. Conversely, poor middle management can create bottlenecks, stifle creativity, and cause disengagement, ultimately leading to attrition and stagnation.</p>
<p id="3eaf" class="pw-post-body-paragraph mg mh ha mi b mj mk ml mm mn mo mp mq mr ms mt mu mv mw mx my mz na nb nc nd gp bk" data-selectable-paragraph="">Organizations that undervalue middle managers risk missing out on their most significant leverage points for change. Leadership teams set the vision, but it is middle management that makes change stick. The bravest among them create feedback loops to share the “ground-truth” that leaders could never see. The real work of organizational transformation — whether it be cultural shifts, Agile adoption, or strategic pivots — lives in the day-to-day decisions and interactions managed at the working level.</p>
<p id="df79" class="pw-post-body-paragraph mg mh ha mi b mj mk ml mm mn mo mp mq mr ms mt mu mv mw mx my mz na nb nc nd gp bk" data-selectable-paragraph="">When innovation originates at the team level and complexity outstrips top-down decision-making, the question isn’t whether middle management is relevant. The question is how the role can work to meet the evolving needs of organizations. This evolution requires us to think of middle management not as a title but as a discipline — a practice rooted in enabling others, fostering collaboration, and shaping environments where knowledge and creativity thrive.</p>
<p id="ad4c" class="pw-post-body-paragraph mg mh ha mi b mj mk ml mm mn mo mp mq mr ms mt mu mv mw mx my mz na nb nc nd gp bk" data-selectable-paragraph=""><strong class="mi hb">From Title to Discipline: Middle Managers as Ecosystem Architects</strong></p>
<p id="2760" class="pw-post-body-paragraph mg mh ha mi b mj mk ml mm mn mo mp mq mr ms mt mu mv mw mx my mz na nb nc nd gp bk" data-selectable-paragraph="">For much of the 20th century, leadership was synonymous with expertise. Managers were the chess masters, moving pieces with precision, assumed to be the most knowledgeable in the room. But in today’s dynamic work environments, that model is can’t stay true. Innovation and knowledge creation now reside at the team level, where the people closest to the work hold the most up-to-date insights. After all, they are the ones creating and interpreting that knowledge. Through experimentation, incremental work, and reflection, teams refine their contributions in real time.</p>
<p id="f473" class="pw-post-body-paragraph mg mh ha mi b mj mk ml mm mn mo mp mq mr ms mt mu mv mw mx my mz na nb nc nd gp bk" data-selectable-paragraph="">This shift leaves middle managers on the outside. If knowledge is created at the team level, managers simply can’t be the best informed. Their distance from the work makes this impossible. If they can no longer be the most informed decision-makers or technical experts, where can they add the most value?</p>
<p id="dc2a" class="pw-post-body-paragraph mg mh ha mi b mj mk ml mm mn mo mp mq mr ms mt mu mv mw mx my mz na nb nc nd gp bk" data-selectable-paragraph="">This shift redefines the manager’s role from that of a directive authority to an “ecosystem architect,” someone who cultivates the conditions for innovation and collaboration to flourish. Middle managers are not here to dictate; they are here to build. They assemble diverse teams, foster the kinds of teams that dive deep together to uncover new ways to solve hard problems, and create an environment where collective intelligence can thrive.</p>
<p id="68c8" class="pw-post-body-paragraph mg mh ha mi b mj mk ml mm mn mo mp mq mr ms mt mu mv mw mx my mz na nb nc nd gp bk" data-selectable-paragraph="">As architects, middle managers can bridge the micro realities of team dynamics with the macro vision of organizational strategy. They are stewards of the processes, relationships, and cultures that transform individual effort into collective success. They don’t just enforce rules; they design systems that enable creativity and resilience. They act as gardeners of the ecosystem. Just as a gardener can’t will a plant to grow, they can control the environment and selection of plants.</p>
<p id="47d8" class="pw-post-body-paragraph mg mh ha mi b mj mk ml mm mn mo mp mq mr ms mt mu mv mw mx my mz na nb nc nd gp bk" data-selectable-paragraph=""><strong class="mi hb">Leadership as Gardening: Cultivating High-Performing Teams</strong></p>
<p id="3df4" class="pw-post-body-paragraph mg mh ha mi b mj mk ml mm mn mo mp mq mr ms mt mu mv mw mx my mz na nb nc nd gp bk" data-selectable-paragraph="">The idea of leadership as gardening is perhaps best illustrated by U.S. General Stanley McChrystal, who famously redefined leadership during his time commanding the Joint Special Operations Task Force in Iraq. Faced with the fast-evolving landscapes of asymmetric guerrilla warfare, McChrystal realized that traditional, hierarchical command structures were insufficient. His leadership team had to evolve from a ground-war command style to one of distributed decision-making and adaptability.</p>
<p id="ced5" class="pw-post-body-paragraph mg mh ha mi b mj mk ml mm mn mo mp mq mr ms mt mu mv mw mx my mz na nb nc nd gp bk" data-selectable-paragraph="">McChrystal’s approach emphasized the need to cultivate environments where informed decisions could be made at all levels. Similarly, effective middle managers enable teams to adapt, innovate, and thrive in complex, dynamic environments — though surely with significantly less immediate stakes.</p>
<p id="a7b6" class="pw-post-body-paragraph mg mh ha mi b mj mk ml mm mn mo mp mq mr ms mt mu mv mw mx my mz na nb nc nd gp bk" data-selectable-paragraph="">In organizations where ideas are the most valuable resource, middle managers act as gardeners nurturing thriving ecosystems. Middle managers, as gardeners of organizational ecosystems, take on a craft-oriented role, carefully shaping teams, processes, cultures, and norms to foster sustainable growth and innovation. Gardening is not passive; it requires intentional effort to balance competing priorities and ensure the ecosystem thrives as a whole.</p>
<p id="c9e2" class="pw-post-body-paragraph mg mh ha mi b mj mk ml mm mn mo mp mq mr ms mt mu mv mw mx my mz na nb nc nd gp bk" data-selectable-paragraph="">Just as a gardener must weed out invasive plants that threaten the harmony of the garden, middle managers address behaviours or dynamics that disrupt team cohesion or effectiveness. They prune back certain aspects of processes or team interactions to create space for others to flourish, knowing that overgrowth in one area can overshadow critical contributions elsewhere. Similarly, they choose what to plant — assembling teams with diverse, complementary skills, perspectives, and strengths. This deliberate curation ensures that the soil of the team — its collective intelligence — is enriched and balanced, promoting long-term health and productivity.</p>
<p id="32f0" class="pw-post-body-paragraph mg mh ha mi b mj mk ml mm mn mo mp mq mr ms mt mu mv mw mx my mz na nb nc nd gp bk" data-selectable-paragraph=""><strong class="mi hb">Cultivating Psychological Safety</strong></p>
<p id="7792" class="pw-post-body-paragraph mg mh ha mi b mj mk ml mm mn mo mp mq mr ms mt mu mv mw mx my mz na nb nc nd gp bk" data-selectable-paragraph="">More important than anything else, middle managers must cultivate psychological safety within their teams. As Amy Edmondson emphasizes in her book <em class="ne">Teaming</em>, this involves fostering an environment where team members feel comfortable taking risks, voicing concerns, and learning from mistakes without fear of judgment or retribution.</p>
<p id="f7b5" class="pw-post-body-paragraph mg mh ha mi b mj mk ml mm mn mo mp mq mr ms mt mu mv mw mx my mz na nb nc nd gp bk" data-selectable-paragraph="">This isn’t merely about avoiding blame or punishment but about shaping the very dynamics of how the team operates. Think of it like a game of strategic interaction. In a traditional, hierarchical setting, the default strategy for team members might be to prioritize self-preservation. Challenging a flawed idea or proposing a radical solution carries significant risks: potential embarrassment, social ostracization, or even career damage. The “payoff” for this risk-averse behavior is minimal — maintaining the status quo, avoiding conflict, and ensuring personal safety.</p>
<p id="3e19" class="pw-post-body-paragraph mg mh ha mi b mj mk ml mm mn mo mp mq mr ms mt mu mv mw mx my mz na nb nc nd gp bk" data-selectable-paragraph="">This dynamic mirrors Rousseau’s classic <em class="ne">Stag Hunt</em>. In this scenario, a group of hunters can either cooperate to hunt a large stag, providing a bountiful feast for all, or individually hunt for hares, guaranteeing a smaller but certain meal. If all hunters cooperate and focus on the stag, they achieve the optimal outcome. However, if even one hunter defects and pursues a hare, the stag will escape, leaving all with only meagre rabbit meat (which if hunters eat exclusively, they will perish from what is known a <em class="ne">rabbit starvation</em>).</p>
<p id="7157" class="pw-post-body-paragraph mg mh ha mi b mj mk ml mm mn mo mp mq mr ms mt mu mv mw mx my mz na nb nc nd gp bk" data-selectable-paragraph="">In the absence of a shared understanding of the collective goal and a culture of trust and mutual support, individual self-interest often prevails. Team members, fearing the potential consequences of challenging the status quo or taking risks, opt for the safe option — pursuing individual goals or maintaining the status quo. This leads to a suboptimal outcome for the entire team, hindering innovation, stifling creativity, and ultimately limiting the team’s ability to achieve its full potential.</p>
<p id="82c3" class="pw-post-body-paragraph mg mh ha mi b mj mk ml mm mn mo mp mq mr ms mt mu mv mw mx my mz na nb nc nd gp bk" data-selectable-paragraph="">By cultivating a culture of psychological safety, middle managers can shift the game. They can raise the potential rewards for challenging the status quo while simultaneously lowering the negative consequences. This creates a virtuous cycle where:</p>
<ul class="">
<li id="faaa" class="mg mh ha mi b mj mk ml mm mn mo mp mq mr ms mt mu mv mw mx my mz na nb nc nd nf ng nh bk" data-selectable-paragraph="">Challenging ideas becomes the expected norm: Team members are encouraged to question assumptions, offer constructive criticism, and engage in open debate.</li>
<li id="e370" class="mg mh ha mi b mj ni ml mm mn nj mp mq mr nk mt mu mv nl mx my mz nm nb nc nd nf ng nh bk" data-selectable-paragraph="">Collective intelligence flourishes: Diverse perspectives are valued, and the team leverages the combined knowledge and creativity of its members to achieve better outcomes.</li>
<li id="927d" class="mg mh ha mi b mj ni ml mm mn nj mp mq mr nk mt mu mv nl mx my mz nm nb nc nd nf ng nh bk" data-selectable-paragraph="">Learning and innovation thrive: A culture of experimentation and learning from both successes and failures becomes embedded in the team’s DNA.</li>
</ul>
<p id="4097" class="pw-post-body-paragraph mg mh ha mi b mj mk ml mm mn mo mp mq mr ms mt mu mv mw mx my mz na nb nc nd gp bk" data-selectable-paragraph=""><strong class="mi hb">The Practical Value of Middle Management</strong></p>
<p id="751c" class="pw-post-body-paragraph mg mh ha mi b mj mk ml mm mn mo mp mq mr ms mt mu mv mw mx my mz na nb nc nd gp bk" data-selectable-paragraph="">By consciously shaping the social and interpersonal dynamics within their teams and cultivating a culture of trust and openness, middle managers can unlock the full potential of their teams and drive high performance.</p>
<p id="b4a7" class="pw-post-body-paragraph mg mh ha mi b mj mk ml mm mn mo mp mq mr ms mt mu mv mw mx my mz na nb nc nd gp bk" data-selectable-paragraph="">Beyond assembling the right people and cultivating psychological safety, middle managers also:</p>
<ul class="">
<li id="0a3b" class="mg mh ha mi b mj mk ml mm mn mo mp mq mr ms mt mu mv mw mx my mz na nb nc nd nf ng nh bk" data-selectable-paragraph=""><strong class="mi hb">Facilitate continuous learning</strong>: They create opportunities for reflection, experimentation, and knowledge sharing within and across teams. This might involve organizing workshops, team retrospectives, or knowledge-sharing sessions.</li>
<li id="2ea1" class="mg mh ha mi b mj ni ml mm mn nj mp mq mr nk mt mu mv nl mx my mz nm nb nc nd nf ng nh bk" data-selectable-paragraph=""><strong class="mi hb">Build and maintain team networks</strong>: Middle managers help their teams connect with other teams, departments, and external stakeholders, fostering collaboration and access to diverse perspectives.</li>
<li id="2a99" class="mg mh ha mi b mj ni ml mm mn nj mp mq mr nk mt mu mv nl mx my mz nm nb nc nd nf ng nh bk" data-selectable-paragraph=""><strong class="mi hb">Adapt to changing circumstances</strong>: In today’s dynamic environment, middle managers must be agile and adaptable, supporting their teams as they navigate uncertainty and adjust to new challenges.</li>
</ul>
<p id="be59" class="pw-post-body-paragraph mg mh ha mi b mj mk ml mm mn mo mp mq mr ms mt mu mv mw mx my mz na nb nc nd gp bk" data-selectable-paragraph="">In this ecosystem, the manager’s role is not to dictate but to facilitate. They encourage cross-pollination of ideas by connecting teams across silos, ensuring that insights flow freely throughout the organization. They also act as guardians of focus, shielding their teams from unnecessary distractions while keeping them aligned with strategic priorities.</p>
<p id="96de" class="pw-post-body-paragraph mg mh ha mi b mj mk ml mm mn mo mp mq mr ms mt mu mv mw mx my mz na nb nc nd gp bk" data-selectable-paragraph=""><strong class="mi hb">Investing in Teams: Lessons from Google</strong></p>
<p id="1044" class="pw-post-body-paragraph mg mh ha mi b mj mk ml mm mn mo mp mq mr ms mt mu mv mw mx my mz na nb nc nd gp bk" data-selectable-paragraph="">This is not simply a well-meaning or moral idea; it has real implications for organizational success. For example, tech companies like Google show us how valuable cohesive teams are in the knowledge economy. Their billion-dollar acquisitions aren’t just about technology — they’re about acquiring the brilliant teams behind that technology. When Google buys a firm like Raxium, it’s not just snapping up a product; it’s also bringing in the people who built it. A $1 billion purchase of a 50-person team? That’s $20 million per employee — proof that they value the people as much as, if not more than, the product itself.</p>
<p id="ea79" class="pw-post-body-paragraph mg mh ha mi b mj mk ml mm mn mo mp mq mr ms mt mu mv mw mx my mz na nb nc nd gp bk" data-selectable-paragraph="">Google’s approach to acquisitions reflects a mindset shift. They know that the expertise and creativity of a well-honed team are invaluable. Breezometer, for instance, wasn’t acquired solely for its air quality monitoring service. Even after shutting the product down, Google integrated the team’s knowledge into services like Google Maps. It’s not about the widget; it’s about the people behind it.</p>
<p id="543f" class="pw-post-body-paragraph mg mh ha mi b mj mk ml mm mn mo mp mq mr ms mt mu mv mw mx my mz na nb nc nd gp bk" data-selectable-paragraph=""><strong class="mi hb">Conclusion: The Future of Middle Management</strong></p>
<p id="438f" class="pw-post-body-paragraph mg mh ha mi b mj mk ml mm mn mo mp mq mr ms mt mu mv mw mx my mz na nb nc nd gp bk" data-selectable-paragraph="">Middle management is not a relic of the past but an essential pillar of modern organizations. As knowledge work becomes more complex and dynamic, the role of middle managers must evolve accordingly. Their value lies not in control, but in cultivation — shaping the conditions that enable teams to thrive, adapt, and innovate.</p>
<p id="f18b" class="pw-post-body-paragraph mg mh ha mi b mj mk ml mm mn mo mp mq mr ms mt mu mv mw mx my mz na nb nc nd gp bk" data-selectable-paragraph="">The most effective middle managers are not bureaucratic bottlenecks but ecosystem architects, balancing autonomy with alignment and fostering environments where collective intelligence flourishes. They facilitate learning, remove obstacles, and build the connective tissue that allows organizations to harness the full potential of their people.</p>
<p id="31ae" class="pw-post-body-paragraph mg mh ha mi b mj mk ml mm mn mo mp mq mr ms mt mu mv mw mx my mz na nb nc nd gp bk" data-selectable-paragraph="">Far from being obsolete, middle management is more critical than ever. The organizations that recognize this — and invest in developing managers as enablers of high-performing teams — will be the ones that navigate complexity and change with the greatest agility. The future of work will not be shaped by rigid hierarchies, but by those who understand that leadership is less about directing and more about designing the right conditions for success. Hopefully with great mutual respect between themselves and agile coaches / scrum masters (the author wrote with no hidden personal agenda.)</p>
            ]]>
        </content>
    </entry>
    <entry>
        <title>Diversity, Complexity and Disappointed Optimists</title>
        <author>
            <name>Liam Shaw</name>
        </author>
        <link href="https://atlancia.com/diversity-complexity-and-disappointed-optimists.html"/>
        <id>https://atlancia.com/diversity-complexity-and-disappointed-optimists.html</id>
        <media:content url="https://atlancia.com/media/posts/4/diverse-header.jpg" medium="image" />

        <updated>2023-06-05T00:00:00-04:00</updated>
            <summary>
                <![CDATA[
                        <img src="https://atlancia.com/media/posts/4/diverse-header.jpg" alt="" />
                    In many creative activities the medium of execution is intractable. Lumber splits; paints smear; electrical circuits ring. These physical limitations of the medium constrain the ideas that may be expressed, and they also create unexpected difficulties in the implementation. Implementation, then, takes time and sweat&hellip;
                ]]>
            </summary>
        <content type="html">
            <![CDATA[
                    <p><img src="https://atlancia.com/media/posts/4/diverse-header.jpg" class="type:primaryImage" alt="" /></p>
                <div class="ac cb">
<div class="ci bh gb gc gd ge">
<blockquote class="mg mh mi">
<p id="5425" class="mj mk ml mm b mn mo mp mq mr ms mt mu mv mw mx my mz na nb nc nd ne nf ng nh gp bk" data-selectable-paragraph="">In many creative activities the medium of execution is intractable. Lumber splits; paints smear; electrical circuits ring. These physical limitations of the medium constrain the ideas that may be expressed, and they also create unexpected difficulties in the implementation.</p>
<p id="8028" class="mj mk ml mm b mn mo mp mq mr ms mt mu mv mw mx my mz na nb nc nd ne nf ng nh gp bk" data-selectable-paragraph="">Implementation, then, takes time and sweat both because of the physical media and because of the inadequacies of the underlying ideas. We tend to blame the physical media for most of our implementation difficulties; for the media are not “ours” in the way the ideas are, and our pride colors our judgment.</p>
<p id="25d1" class="mj mk ml mm b mn mo mp mq mr ms mt mu mv mw mx my mz na nb nc nd ne nf ng nh gp bk" data-selectable-paragraph="">- “The Mythical Man Month” — Fred Brooks, 1975</p>
</blockquote>
<p id="bcd6" class="pw-post-body-paragraph mj mk ha mm b mn mo mp mq mr ms mt mu mv mw mx my mz na nb nc nd ne nf ng nh gp bk" data-selectable-paragraph="">In the nearly half century since Fred Brooks articulated the idea of a “mythical man month,” the myth persists. He attributed the myth to optimism, that software development is a “modern sorcery [that] especially attracts those who believe in happy endings and fairy godmothers.”</p>
<p id="6320" class="pw-post-body-paragraph mj mk ha mm b mn mo mp mq mr ms mt mu mv mw mx my mz na nb nc nd ne nf ng nh gp bk" data-selectable-paragraph="">The persistent mythology, that if we close our eyes, and think hard enough, that we can put together a perfectly tractable plan of what we want to build, how we can build it and who will need to pull it together, is an optimistic delusion. This optimism has real consequences, and I’ve witnessed language used by those concerned with diversity that reflects this as a foundation for some of their resistance to accepting diversity and inclusion not simply as a moral imperative, but as a benefit to improved performance.</p>
<p id="ad33" class="pw-post-body-paragraph mj mk ha mm b mn mo mp mq mr ms mt mu mv mw mx my mz na nb nc nd ne nf ng nh gp bk" data-selectable-paragraph="">In today’s ever changing and interconnected world, organizations are facing the challenge of complex work environments. More and more work is shifting from the complicated (difficult to fully grasp, but possible to learn over time) to the complex (highly interdependent and variable). Through this, I’ll make an effort to draw lines from complexity, management theory and diversity together into a mental model to add context to the relationship between diversity, inclusion, and collaboration in the context of complex work.</p>
<h1 id="38e8" class="ni nj ha bf nk nl nm nn no np nq nr ns nt nu nv nw nx ny nz oa ob oc od oe of bk" data-selectable-paragraph="">The Complicated and the Complex</h1>
<figure class="post__image post__image--center" ><img loading="lazy" src="https://atlancia.com/media/posts/4/diverse-1.webp" alt="" width="1046" height="1067" sizes="(max-width: 1920px) 100vw, 1920px" srcset="https://atlancia.com/media/posts/4/responsive/diverse-1-xs.webp 640w ,https://atlancia.com/media/posts/4/responsive/diverse-1-sm.webp 768w ,https://atlancia.com/media/posts/4/responsive/diverse-1-md.webp 1024w ,https://atlancia.com/media/posts/4/responsive/diverse-1-lg.webp 1366w ,https://atlancia.com/media/posts/4/responsive/diverse-1-xl.webp 1600w ,https://atlancia.com/media/posts/4/responsive/diverse-1-2xl.webp 1920w">
<figcaption ><em class="pd">Simplified Stacey Matrix (also known as Stacey Complexity Model)</em></figcaption>
</figure>
<p id="c5a3" class="pw-post-body-paragraph mj mk ha mm b mn mo mp mq mr ms mt mu mv mw mx my mz na nb nc nd ne nf ng nh gp bk" data-selectable-paragraph="">As a starting point for moving further, I have to start with a few definitions.</p>
<ul class="">
<li id="2a92" class="mj mk ha mm b mn mo mp mq mr ms mt mu mv mw mx my mz na nb nc nd ne nf ng nh pe pf pg bk" data-selectable-paragraph="">We’ll take the idea of a “simple” problem as one in which there is a single optimal peak; the optimal weight of a shovel-full of coal to unload a cart in a 12 hour shift.</li>
<li id="dd45" class="mj mk ha mm b mn ph mp mq mr pi mt mu mv pj mx my mz pk nb nc nd pl nf ng nh pe pf pg bk" data-selectable-paragraph="">A complicated problem where there may be multiple “good” solutions and one “optimal” solution but once they are discovered through training and experience, they remain optimal. Imagine watch repair, there are multiple strategies for diagnosis and repair, but with enough experience a repair-person can find at least a personal (local) optimum.</li>
<li id="f18e" class="mj mk ha mm b mn ph mp mq mr pi mt mu mv pj mx my mz pk nb nc nd pl nf ng nh pe pf pg bk" data-selectable-paragraph="">And finally, the complex and chaotic environments of the dancing landscapes, in which optimums can only temporarily be discovered, a peak today may not be a peak tomorrow, an optimum may not be an optimum in a year, etc. An easy example would be financial markets, where any sufficiently good strategy, ceases to be a good strategy once other parties wise up to it (Adaptive Market Hypothesis).</li>
</ul>
<figure ><figure class="post__image post__image--center"><img loading="lazy"  src="https://atlancia.com/media/posts/4/diverse-2.webp" alt="" width="1118" height="602" sizes="(max-width: 1920px) 100vw, 1920px" srcset="https://atlancia.com/media/posts/4/responsive/diverse-2-xs.webp 640w ,https://atlancia.com/media/posts/4/responsive/diverse-2-sm.webp 768w ,https://atlancia.com/media/posts/4/responsive/diverse-2-md.webp 1024w ,https://atlancia.com/media/posts/4/responsive/diverse-2-lg.webp 1366w ,https://atlancia.com/media/posts/4/responsive/diverse-2-xl.webp 1600w ,https://atlancia.com/media/posts/4/responsive/diverse-2-2xl.webp 1920w"></figure>
<figcaption >From <em class="pd">Investigating Emergent Design Failures Using a Knowledge-Action-Decision Framework </em>by Colin P. F. Shields</figcaption>
</figure>
<h1 id="e853" class="ni nj ha bf nk nl nm nn no np nq nr ns nt nu nv nw nx ny nz oa ob oc od oe of bk" data-selectable-paragraph="">Kicking and Screaming Into Complexity</h1>
<figure class="post__image post__image--center">Regardless of how we choose to encode the ideas of complexity, either the above, or other common models like Cynefin, the key idea is that there is a point in complexity where we leave the world of the predictable, stable and solvable and enter a different domain.
<img loading="lazy"  src="https://atlancia.com/media/posts/4/diverse-3.webp" alt="" width="1600" height="1334" sizes="(max-width: 1920px) 100vw, 1920px" srcset="https://atlancia.com/media/posts/4/responsive/diverse-3-xs.webp 640w ,https://atlancia.com/media/posts/4/responsive/diverse-3-sm.webp 768w ,https://atlancia.com/media/posts/4/responsive/diverse-3-md.webp 1024w ,https://atlancia.com/media/posts/4/responsive/diverse-3-lg.webp 1366w ,https://atlancia.com/media/posts/4/responsive/diverse-3-xl.webp 1600w ,https://atlancia.com/media/posts/4/responsive/diverse-3-2xl.webp 1920w"></figure>
<p id="f906" class="pw-post-body-paragraph mj mk ha mm b mn mo mp mq mr ms mt mu mv mw mx my mz na nb nc nd ne nf ng nh gp bk" data-selectable-paragraph="">When we traverse across that line, we have to discard many notions that worked in the predictable environment. Best practices become good practices, the very notion that a single practice can be best is a fools errand. Processes become anchors slowing down needed change. Staying still becomes as big a risk as changing, where adaptability is a dimension of organizational resilience (see BS 65000:2022 — Organizational Resilience).</p>
<blockquote class="mg mh mi">
<p id="40ec" class="mj mk ml mm b mn mo mp mq mr ms mt mu mv mw mx my mz na nb nc nd ne nf ng nh gp bk" data-selectable-paragraph=""><em class="ha">All models are wrong, some are useful. — George Box, 1976</em></p>
</blockquote>
<p id="609f" class="pw-post-body-paragraph mj mk ha mm b mn mo mp mq mr ms mt mu mv mw mx my mz na nb nc nd ne nf ng nh gp bk" data-selectable-paragraph="">Amidst the ever-evolving landscape of modern work dynamics the model at hand may indeed falter in numerous aspects, no model will ever be perfect. However, at the heart of this idea lies a pivotal concept: a tipping point where the realm of work is no longer defined by the comfort of predictability, but by the challenges of unpredictability. A paradigm shift that encourages us to re-calibrate our approach. Embracing this metaphoric fault line between divergent landscapes is a challenge.</p>
<h1 id="40ac" class="ni nj ha bf nk nl nm nn no np nq nr ns nt nu nv nw nx ny nz oa ob oc od oe of bk" data-selectable-paragraph="">Sensing Complexity</h1>
<p id="6f1b" class="pw-post-body-paragraph mj mk ha mm b mn pn mp mq mr po mt mu mv pp mx my mz pq nb nc nd pr nf ng nh gp bk" data-selectable-paragraph="">It’s easy to see when it’s on a diagram but how can we sense when we’re working in a complex environment? There is no clear line between the two ideas in real life, with problems don’t come with a label. Some problems have puzzled mathematicians for years with no solution that seem easy but have no solution: the moving sofa problem (What is the largest area of a shape that can be maneuvered through a unit-width L-shaped corridor?) as an example, has no solution.</p>
<p id="6037" class="pw-post-body-paragraph mj mk ha mm b mn mo mp mq mr ms mt mu mv mw mx my mz na nb nc nd ne nf ng nh gp bk" data-selectable-paragraph="">In Nassim Nicolas Taleb’s <em class="ml">Antifragile</em> he offers some indicators that a system is complex. That complex systems are characterized by intricate interdependencies and nonlinear responses. In these systems, doubling a factor does not result in a proportional doubling of the effect but rather an amplified or diminished impact. Simple cause-and-effect relationships do not hold, and understanding the functioning of individual parts alone is insufficient.</p>
<p id="0c1f" class="pw-post-body-paragraph mj mk ha mm b mn mo mp mq mr ms mt mu mv mw mx my mz na nb nc nd ne nf ng nh gp bk" data-selectable-paragraph="">And so, we go full circle. The opening quote of this writing from the <em class="ml">Mythical Man-Month</em>, exemplifies this non-linearity. The conclusion that adding more developers to a late project tends to make them later, is a great indicator that software development, and likely all similarly intangible knowledge work, is complex, not simple or complicated. The rest of the writing will use software development and knowledge work generally, as marquee examples in comparison to other clearly simple or complicated types of work.</p>
<h1 id="6d01" class="ni nj ha bf nk nl nm nn no np nq nr ns nt nu nv nw nx ny nz oa ob oc od oe of bk" data-selectable-paragraph="">Diversity as a Tool in Knowledge Work</h1>
<blockquote class="mg mh mi">
<p id="5d36" class="mj mk ml mm b mn mo mp mq mr ms mt mu mv mw mx my mz na nb nc nd ne nf ng nh gp bk" data-selectable-paragraph=""><em class="ha">Knowledge workers are persons who understand their job better than their boss — Peter Drucker</em></p>
</blockquote>
<p id="403e" class="pw-post-body-paragraph mj mk ha mm b mn mo mp mq mr ms mt mu mv mw mx my mz na nb nc nd ne nf ng nh gp bk" data-selectable-paragraph="">If we are to accept that:</p>
<ul class="">
<li id="d250" class="mj mk ha mm b mn mo mp mq mr ms mt mu mv mw mx my mz na nb nc nd ne nf ng nh pe pf pg bk" data-selectable-paragraph="">Knowledge work is complex and requires teams of skilled people working together</li>
<li id="90b1" class="mj mk ha mm b mn ph mp mq mr pi mt mu mv pj mx my mz pk nb nc nd pl nf ng nh pe pf pg bk" data-selectable-paragraph="">Complex work is unpredictable, interconnected and non-linear</li>
<li id="e893" class="mj mk ha mm b mn ph mp mq mr pi mt mu mv pj mx my mz pk nb nc nd pl nf ng nh pe pf pg bk" data-selectable-paragraph="">The necessary tools required to or expertise to achieve positive results won’t be predictable (at least over a sufficient time space)</li>
</ul>
<p id="6738" class="pw-post-body-paragraph mj mk ha mm b mn mo mp mq mr ms mt mu mv mw mx my mz na nb nc nd ne nf ng nh gp bk" data-selectable-paragraph="">Then surely the natural response would be to seek not to build a team of “qualified” individuals who fit the same mould. Instead, an approach could be to optimize for the broadest germane skills and tools. Diversity of thought, over convergence to a mean.</p>
<p id="bbd5" class="pw-post-body-paragraph mj mk ha mm b mn mo mp mq mr ms mt mu mv mw mx my mz na nb nc nd ne nf ng nh gp bk" data-selectable-paragraph="">Below is a very simplified model built to illustrate some key difference between; making the complicated workings of a watch and the complex development of a novel software product.</p>
</div>
</div>
<div class="gu">
<div class="ac cb">
<div class="lj pt lk pu ll pv cf pw cg px ci bh">
<figure class="post__image post__image--center" ><img loading="lazy" src="https://atlancia.com/media/posts/4/diverse-4.webp" alt="" width="1229" height="830" sizes="(max-width: 1920px) 100vw, 1920px" srcset="https://atlancia.com/media/posts/4/responsive/diverse-4-xs.webp 640w ,https://atlancia.com/media/posts/4/responsive/diverse-4-sm.webp 768w ,https://atlancia.com/media/posts/4/responsive/diverse-4-md.webp 1024w ,https://atlancia.com/media/posts/4/responsive/diverse-4-lg.webp 1366w ,https://atlancia.com/media/posts/4/responsive/diverse-4-xl.webp 1600w ,https://atlancia.com/media/posts/4/responsive/diverse-4-2xl.webp 1920w">
<figcaption >Comparing perspectives and skills; how people bring different ways of understanding and contributing to an outcome.</figcaption>
</figure>
</div>
</div>
</div>
<div class="ac cb">
<div class="ci bh gb gc gd ge">
<p id="8545" class="pw-post-body-paragraph mj mk ha mm b mn mo mp mq mr ms mt mu mv mw mx my mz na nb nc nd ne nf ng nh gp bk" data-selectable-paragraph="">Some key difference that might be visible:</p>
</div>
</div>
<div class="gu">
<div class="ac cb">
<div class="lj pt lk pu ll pv cf pw cg px ci bh"><figure class="post__image post__image--center"><img loading="lazy"  src="https://atlancia.com/media/posts/4/diverse-5.webp" alt="" width="1710" height="1021" sizes="(max-width: 1920px) 100vw, 1920px" srcset="https://atlancia.com/media/posts/4/responsive/diverse-5-xs.webp 640w ,https://atlancia.com/media/posts/4/responsive/diverse-5-sm.webp 768w ,https://atlancia.com/media/posts/4/responsive/diverse-5-md.webp 1024w ,https://atlancia.com/media/posts/4/responsive/diverse-5-lg.webp 1366w ,https://atlancia.com/media/posts/4/responsive/diverse-5-xl.webp 1600w ,https://atlancia.com/media/posts/4/responsive/diverse-5-2xl.webp 1920w"></figure></div>
</div>
</div>
<div class="ac cb">
<div class="ci bh gb gc gd ge">
<p id="8c7e" class="pw-post-body-paragraph mj mk ha mm b mn mo mp mq mr ms mt mu mv mw mx my mz na nb nc nd ne nf ng nh gp bk" data-selectable-paragraph="">The table above almost certainly sells the incredible skills of watchmaking short, but as a model, the key ideas hopefully hold up. The key concepts that we can tease out though are:</p>
<ul class="">
<li id="7045" class="mj mk ha mm b mn mo mp mq mr ms mt mu mv mw mx my mz na nb nc nd ne nf ng nh pe pf pg bk" data-selectable-paragraph="">The outcome of work; the product, requires collaboration between team members with multiple skills where individual contribution alone cannot produce value</li>
<li id="e432" class="mj mk ha mm b mn ph mp mq mr pi mt mu mv pj mx my mz pk nb nc nd pl nf ng nh pe pf pg bk" data-selectable-paragraph="">The skills needed to complete work usually require a breadth of skills and knowledge beyond a single individual’s capacity; a typical flow of requirements, design, implement, test and deploy may require all of the roles in the diagram to work together</li>
<li id="01bd" class="mj mk ha mm b mn ph mp mq mr pi mt mu mv pj mx my mz pk nb nc nd pl nf ng nh pe pf pg bk" data-selectable-paragraph="">The relationship between the team and the work isn’t predictable, some work may require a large amount of design, some may require extremely in-depth knowledge of development or knowledge of a new business domain.</li>
</ul>
<figure class="post__image post__image--center">Unpredictability in work, needed skills/knowledge and the inter-connectedness of a individuals on a team mean that a viable strategy to strengthen a team is to pursue adding to existing skills, but also add diverse perspectives and heuristics. A team might look at what upcoming work is coming and ask themselves what perspectives are missing to address the work.
<img loading="lazy"  src="https://atlancia.com/media/posts/4/diverse-6.webp" alt="" width="2003" height="1663" sizes="(max-width: 1920px) 100vw, 1920px" srcset="https://atlancia.com/media/posts/4/responsive/diverse-6-xs.webp 640w ,https://atlancia.com/media/posts/4/responsive/diverse-6-sm.webp 768w ,https://atlancia.com/media/posts/4/responsive/diverse-6-md.webp 1024w ,https://atlancia.com/media/posts/4/responsive/diverse-6-lg.webp 1366w ,https://atlancia.com/media/posts/4/responsive/diverse-6-xl.webp 1600w ,https://atlancia.com/media/posts/4/responsive/diverse-6-2xl.webp 1920w"></figure>
<p id="1873" class="pw-post-body-paragraph mj mk ha mm b mn mo mp mq mr ms mt mu mv mw mx my mz na nb nc nd ne nf ng nh gp bk" data-selectable-paragraph="">Say this team had to balance two very big pieces of work in their system: a large security issue and a challenging high priority feature request. What could they do as a first step? Look at the new work and ask themselves, what they might be missing to address them, and seek out adding that to the team. It is only the team though who could assess this as it is based on their collective skills.</p>
<p id="f2ba" class="pw-post-body-paragraph mj mk ha mm b mn mo mp mq mr ms mt mu mv mw mx my mz na nb nc nd ne nf ng nh gp bk" data-selectable-paragraph="">Let’s assume the team looks inward and decides they need to add a new member to address these two needs. It’s likely they come to a conclusion that the new member should not have the same background as themselves. Additionally, if they foresee that future work will require this same bringing in of new knowledge, then the optimal approach of who to bring in is to bring someone in who looks like the least like them with the most different perspectives and heuristics.</p>
<p id="6526" class="pw-post-body-paragraph mj mk ha mm b mn mo mp mq mr ms mt mu mv mw mx my mz na nb nc nd ne nf ng nh gp bk" data-selectable-paragraph="">Cognitive diversity builds their capacity to address the problems of today and better position themselves to address problems in the future.</p>
<h1 id="27d5" class="ni nj ha bf nk nl nm nn no np nq nr ns nt nu nv nw nx ny nz oa ob oc od oe of bk" data-selectable-paragraph="">Sympathy for the Devil</h1>
<p id="5427" class="pw-post-body-paragraph mj mk ha mm b mn pn mp mq mr po mt mu mv pp mx my mz pq nb nc nd pr nf ng nh gp bk" data-selectable-paragraph="">When I imagine a worker spending all day shovelling coal, seeing their daily pay and seeing a smaller pile of coal next to theirs done by another worker paid the same it doesn’t feel like a stretch to imagine the discontentment they may feel. The same might be felt by a craftsman who built a watch (or more watches) of higher quality than a peer who also was paid the same. In these environments, perhaps some discontentment that a “diversity hire” could be brought in may feel a little more justified.</p>
<p id="7150" class="pw-post-body-paragraph mj mk ha mm b mn mo mp mq mr ms mt mu mv mw mx my mz na nb nc nd ne nf ng nh gp bk" data-selectable-paragraph="">However, when looking at knowledge work, where complexity is the norm, how can we justify that same sentiment? I’d argue that we simply can’t. The volatility, uncertainty, complexity, and ambiguity of the work environment ought to compel teams to add skills different from their own as a route to making themselves and their teams better. Holding onto notions of strict “qualifications” serve to limit the pool of perspectives and tools that teams may have access to. Certainly, there’s a need to retain germane skills but when work requires increasing breadth of knowledge can we reasonably expect to address new challenges by bringing in people who look, act and work just like us?</p>
</div>
</div>
            ]]>
        </content>
    </entry>
    <entry>
        <title>Building a Trade-off Mentality</title>
        <author>
            <name>Liam Shaw</name>
        </author>
        <link href="https://atlancia.com/building-a-trade-off-mentality.html"/>
        <id>https://atlancia.com/building-a-trade-off-mentality.html</id>
        <media:content url="https://atlancia.com/media/posts/3/tradeoffpost.jpg" medium="image" />

        <updated>2023-05-06T00:00:00-04:00</updated>
            <summary>
                <![CDATA[
                        <img src="https://atlancia.com/media/posts/3/tradeoffpost.jpg" alt="" />
                    If you wish to make an apple pie from scratch, you must first invent the universe. – Carl Sagan Carl Sagan’s famous quote inspires deeper thought of how connected our universe is, that to “make an apple pie from scratch” you can keep going one&hellip;
                ]]>
            </summary>
        <content type="html">
            <![CDATA[
                    <p><img src="https://atlancia.com/media/posts/3/tradeoffpost.jpg" class="type:primaryImage" alt="" /></p>
                <blockquote class="uy uz va">
<p id="a616" class="vb vc vd ve b vf vg vh vi vj vk vl vm vn vo vp vq vr vs vt vu vv vw vx vy vz ga bk align-left" data-selectable-paragraph=""><em class="qk">If you wish to make an apple pie from scratch, you must first invent the universe.<br><span class="_97w2Z3njlMm7Og_zyqu4">– </span>Carl Sagan</em></p>
</blockquote>
<p id="f521" class="pw-post-body-paragraph vb vc qk ve b vf vg vh vi vj vk vl vm vn vo vp vq vr vs vt vu vv vw vx vy vz ga bk" data-selectable-paragraph="">Carl Sagan’s famous quote inspires deeper thought of how connected our universe is, that to “make an apple pie from scratch” you can keep going one step backwards until one has to “invent the universe.” What struck me was, that somewhere between the start of the universe and baking the pie, we had to draw a line for what we consider “from scratch.” Why would buying pre-made pie crust feel like “cheating,” yet buying pre-ground flour would not? What lines have we drawn without much thought of how we choose them?</p>
<p id="34b1" class="pw-post-body-paragraph vb vc qk ve b vf vg vh vi vj vk vl vm vn vo vp vq vr vs vt vu vv vw vx vy vz ga bk" data-selectable-paragraph="">Let’s imagine a manager asking someone to take on a new task. Consider the assumptions that may be at play: the manager assumes the employee can do the task, will listen, will understand, and could do the work without sacrificing their current efforts. What trade-offs are involved? What work might suffer to focus on this new task? How would the manager or the employee differ in their views of what could be dropped to accommodate the new work and what might those different opinions tell us about what each of them values?</p>
<p id="b657" class="pw-post-body-paragraph vb vc qk ve b vf vg vh vi vj vk vl vm vn vo vp vq vr vs vt vu vv vw vx vy vz ga bk" data-selectable-paragraph="">I’ve found it useful to ask myself what assumptions I’m making when I make a statement. This approach helps me identify what trade-offs and assumed truths may need to be evaluated to see if they’re still true. However, within my head, I can take a far more confrontational approach to my thoughts than I may with others. Thus, I worked on trying out a more inquisitive approach using a mental toolkit that I call the “trade-off mentality” as a way to more collaboratively uncover inbuilt assumptions and have open discussions about the underlying rationale behind our decisions, preferences and assumptions.</p>
<p id="60b8" class="pw-post-body-paragraph vb vc qk ve b vf vg vh vi vj vk vl vm vn vo vp vq vr vs vt vu vv vw vx vy vz ga bk" data-selectable-paragraph="">While I do believe this is a general toolkit that has helped me think better across multiple domains, the focus in the text below will be largely on software development and teams.</p>
<p id="eef6" class="pw-post-body-paragraph vb vc qk ve b vf vg vh vi vj vk vl vm vn vo vp vq vr vs vt vu vv vw vx vy vz ga bk" data-selectable-paragraph="">This mental toolkit is based on four core ideas:</p>
<ul class="">
<li id="f85d" class="vb vc qk ve b vf vg vh vi vj vk vl vm vn vo vp vq vr vs vt vu vv vw vx vy vz wa wb wc bk" data-selectable-paragraph="">First, there ain’t no such thing as a free lunch — we cannot simply get something without giving something up.</li>
<li id="93c7" class="vb vc qk ve b vf wd vh vi vj we vl vm vn wf vp vq vr wg vt vu vv wh vx vy vz wa wb wc bk" data-selectable-paragraph="">Second, trade-offs allow us to question what we value.</li>
<li id="3291" class="vb vc qk ve b vf wd vh vi vj we vl vm vn wf vp vq vr wg vt vu vv wh vx vy vz wa wb wc bk" data-selectable-paragraph="">Third, trade-offs offer an opportunity for us to discuss ways of splitting or breaking down things we bundle together or associate.</li>
<li id="dabc" class="vb vc qk ve b vf wd vh vi vj we vl vm vn wf vp vq vr wg vt vu vv wh vx vy vz wa wb wc bk" data-selectable-paragraph="">Finally, when we evaluate decisions and assumptions, we can gain additional insight by asking ourselves who is being served by balancing and weighing valuations.</li>
</ul>
<h1 id="d900" class="wi wj qk bf wk lb wl lc le lf wm lg li in wn io ir ll wo lm lp lq wp lr lu wq bk" data-selectable-paragraph="">Idea 1: There ain’t no such thing as a free lunch</h1>
<p id="4c61" class="pw-post-body-paragraph vb vc qk ve b vf wr vh vi vj ws vl vm vn wt vp vq vr wu vt vu vv wv vx vy vz ga bk" data-selectable-paragraph="">Central to the first idea is the acknowledgement that all endeavours entail a cost and are bound by constraints. That we cannot get a “free lunch.” Choosing to stay up late to watch another episode of Succession, means accepting you might be a little tired tomorrow. We are constrained by time, energy, money, and many other limits.</p>
<p id="1728" class="pw-post-body-paragraph vb vc qk ve b vf vg vh vi vj vk vl vm vn vo vp vq vr vs vt vu vv vw vx vy vz ga bk" data-selectable-paragraph="">For instance, we can look at even subtle constraints to a team’s productivity. My favourite to consider is the cognitive load incurred by increasing work complexity (or simply using the idea of mental energy). Such complexity may hinder growth, or necessitate trade-offs in terms of longer learning, more challenging onboarding, or higher rates of incidents. Surfacing impacts from complexity could help identify future challenges and uncover risks we might not be willing to accept.</p>
<p id="abcd" class="pw-post-body-paragraph vb vc qk ve b vf vg vh vi vj vk vl vm vn vo vp vq vr vs vt vu vv vw vx vy vz ga bk" data-selectable-paragraph="">Indicator statements such as: “We should make time for training,” “I would like you to deliver this as well,” or “The team must assume accountability for this new system” may serve as potential triggers for conversations on underlying assumptions and required trade-offs. The figure below shows a hypothetical model of transition for a team taking on a new application, in which a new idea comes to mind — the “cost” of assuming new accountabilities.</p>
<figure class="post__image post__image--center"><img loading="lazy"  src="https://atlancia.com/media/posts/3/state-view.webp" alt="" width="2317" height="939" sizes="(max-width: 1920px) 100vw, 1920px" srcset="https://atlancia.com/media/posts/3/responsive/state-view-xs.webp 640w ,https://atlancia.com/media/posts/3/responsive/state-view-sm.webp 768w ,https://atlancia.com/media/posts/3/responsive/state-view-md.webp 1024w ,https://atlancia.com/media/posts/3/responsive/state-view-lg.webp 1366w ,https://atlancia.com/media/posts/3/responsive/state-view-xl.webp 1600w ,https://atlancia.com/media/posts/3/responsive/state-view-2xl.webp 1920w"></figure>
<p id="0d62" class="pw-post-body-paragraph vb vc qk ve b vf vg vh vi vj vk vl vm vn vo vp vq vr vs vt vu vv vw vx vy vz ga bk" data-selectable-paragraph="">A classic trade-off in systems development, for example, is the balance between investing in new features versus reducing technical debt. A team’s ability to discuss and evaluate these classic trade-offs can have a significant impact on their long-term success. Investments in technical debt reduction, while not as glamorous as new features, can often lead to more sustainable development and increased capacity for future innovation.</p>
<p id="bb5b" class="pw-post-body-paragraph vb vc qk ve b vf vg vh vi vj vk vl vm vn vo vp vq vr vs vt vu vv vw vx vy vz ga bk" data-selectable-paragraph="">By carefully examining statements, especially those that indicate a “more X” is possible, we can surface implicit assumptions and trade-offs, while individuals and teams can better understand the consequences of their decisions and align their actions with their values and goals.</p>
<h1 id="3055" class="wi wj qk bf wk lb wl lc le lf wm lg li in wn io ir ll wo lm lp lq wp lr lu wq bk" data-selectable-paragraph="">Idea 2: Trade-off decisions offer a space to inspect values</h1>
<p id="8949" class="pw-post-body-paragraph vb vc qk ve b vf wr vh vi vj ws vl vm vn wt vp vq vr wu vt vu vv wv vx vy vz ga bk" data-selectable-paragraph="">When confronted with a potential trade-off, we have a space to ask ourselves, “Why did I choose X over Y?” Is that choice consistent with my values? With a team’s values? With an organization’s goals?</p>
<p id="b8ec" class="pw-post-body-paragraph vb vc qk ve b vf vg vh vi vj vk vl vm vn vo vp vq vr vs vt vu vv vw vx vy vz ga bk" data-selectable-paragraph="">The act of questioning myself has helped me gain insight into my own beliefs and assumptions. When considering whether to speak up in a group setting, for instance, I consider if I am preventing someone else from contributing or if simply presenting an opinion may discourage dissenting viewpoints. Even the subtle act of supporting an idea may make dissenting viewpoints harder to bring forward.</p>
<p id="eed0" class="pw-post-body-paragraph vb vc qk ve b vf vg vh vi vj vk vl vm vn vo vp vq vr vs vt vu vv vw vx vy vz ga bk" data-selectable-paragraph="">When faced with a difficult decision, individuals may engage in a process of introspection, carefully evaluating the relative importance of the available options and the factors that inform those values. This process can be particularly valuable in group settings where individuals with different skill sets and viewpoints must navigate trade-offs to achieve a common goal.</p>
<p id="b429" class="pw-post-body-paragraph vb vc qk ve b vf vg vh vi vj vk vl vm vn vo vp vq vr vs vt vu vv vw vx vy vz ga bk" data-selectable-paragraph="">But, evaluating trade-offs is not just an individual activity. Teams and organizations can also benefit from examining the trade-offs they make in pursuit of their goals. By holding up a mirror to themselves and asking if they are truly living up to their values, teams can identify areas for improvement and develop strategies to better align their actions with their goals. For example, a team tasked with reporting weekly on their progress may be trading off valuable development time and energy for the sake of reporting. By examining this trade-off, the team could question which benefits of reporting outweigh the costs and adjust their approach accordingly.</p>
<p id="6ec9" class="pw-post-body-paragraph vb vc qk ve b vf vg vh vi vj vk vl vm vn vo vp vq vr vs vt vu vv vw vx vy vz ga bk" data-selectable-paragraph="">This particular idea may be more difficult to have an open dialogue about because it may challenge deeply held assumptions. Two areas I have had difficult discussions about have been the topics of reporting and options analysis. If we believe our value is to deliver work and support clients/customers/users, both would be “wastes” from a Lean perspective. Options analysis embeds a guarantee of waste; that if N+1 options are presented and 1 option is selected the development of N was largely waste. Softer language, of relative value and checking against objectives, helps serve a less aggressive proposition.</p>
<p id="81f3" class="pw-post-body-paragraph vb vc qk ve b vf vg vh vi vj vk vl vm vn vo vp vq vr vs vt vu vv vw vx vy vz ga bk" data-selectable-paragraph="">Similarly, organizations with a mission to be inclusive may need to examine the trade-offs between objective hiring criteria and the desire to attract a more diverse pool of candidates. Organizations could dig deeper into whether they are truly living up to their values and identify ways to make their processes more equitable and inclusive. Perhaps recognizing that adhering to a strict process may reduce the impact of individual biases while amplifying the impact of structural ones. <em class="vd">e.g. a hiring process that takes 3 months to complete, requires a masters degree and 10 years previous experience excludes the population of people who can’t wait 3 months for a new career and don’t have equitable access to the educational and experience requirements.</em></p>
<p id="b29b" class="pw-post-body-paragraph vb vc qk ve b vf vg vh vi vj vk vl vm vn vo vp vq vr vs vt vu vv vw vx vy vz ga bk" data-selectable-paragraph="">Ultimately, by carefully evaluating the trade-offs we can support, individuals, organizations and teams have more informed decisions and work towards achieving their goals with greater clarity and purpose.</p>
<h1 id="29e5" class="wi wj qk bf wk lb wl lc le lf wm lg li in wn io ir ll wo lm lp lq wp lr lu wq bk" data-selectable-paragraph="">Idea 3: Try to unwrap packages</h1>
<p id="ff1e" class="pw-post-body-paragraph vb vc qk ve b vf wr vh vi vj ws vl vm vn wt vp vq vr wu vt vu vv wv vx vy vz ga bk" data-selectable-paragraph="">One other technique that has been useful when evaluating trade-offs is to do what I have called unwrapping packages. The idea behind this is to unwrap, unbundle and uncouple to make more honest decisions about trade-offs. In the rest of this section, I’ll focus on particular patterns I have found useful to key in on common “bundlings.”</p>
<p id="382c" class="pw-post-body-paragraph vb vc qk ve b vf vg vh vi vj vk vl vm vn vo vp vq vr vs vt vu vv vw vx vy vz ga bk" data-selectable-paragraph="">One such pattern is <em class="vd">association</em>. This pattern involves examining implicit connections we make between ideas. For example, we might assume that working in an office is essential for building strong social connections. While there may be some truth to this, it’s important to recognize that there are other ways to foster social connections. By breaking down these associations we can have more a balanced discussion. In the case of working in an office, the trade-off is not simply between having social connections and staying at home. Instead, it’s about the ease of building connections when we are physically together versus the additional effort required to do so when working remotely.</p>
<p id="bdb7" class="pw-post-body-paragraph vb vc qk ve b vf vg vh vi vj vk vl vm vn vo vp vq vr vs vt vu vv vw vx vy vz ga bk" data-selectable-paragraph="">In this example, we change the discussion from “work from home” vs “connect with new colleagues,” to “work from home and have a more difficult time connecting with new colleagues” vs “go to the office where the friction between meeting new people is lower.” This can support a more nuanced decision, where we can open up dialogue on, for example:</p>
<ul class="">
<li id="1628" class="vb vc qk ve b vf vg vh vi vj vk vl vm vn vo vp vq vr vs vt vu vv vw vx vy vz wa wb wc bk" data-selectable-paragraph="">How to support remote colleagues to form new connections?</li>
<li id="db16" class="vb vc qk ve b vf wd vh vi vj we vl vm vn wf vp vq vr wg vt vu vv wh vx vy vz wa wb wc bk" data-selectable-paragraph="">Why does being in the office encourage more connections and if moving around the building is an important factor, how can we offer that same benefit to less mobile colleagues?</li>
</ul>
<p id="453a" class="pw-post-body-paragraph vb vc qk ve b vf vg vh vi vj vk vl vm vn vo vp vq vr vs vt vu vv vw vx vy vz ga bk" data-selectable-paragraph="">In the world of project management, the concept of a “work package” is all about bundling tasks together into work packages or projects themselves. This approach can be useful in certain situations, particularly when it comes to managing large-scale investments. After all, the bigger the package, the greater the economies of scale that can be achieved (investment governance tends to be roughly equal effort regardless of project sizes).</p>
<p id="fde8" class="pw-post-body-paragraph vb vc qk ve b vf vg vh vi vj vk vl vm vn vo vp vq vr vs vt vu vv vw vx vy vz ga bk" data-selectable-paragraph="">However, there are also cases where this approach might be detrimental. In situations where a team is stable, and tools and solutions are already in place, breaking down tasks into smaller packages can be more effective. This allows for greater flexibility in addressing high-priority items, regardless of where they might fit into a larger package.</p>
<figure class="post__image post__image--center"><img loading="lazy"  src="https://atlancia.com/media/posts/3/selected-view.webp" alt="" width="1953" height="902" sizes="(max-width: 1920px) 100vw, 1920px" srcset="https://atlancia.com/media/posts/3/responsive/selected-view-xs.webp 640w ,https://atlancia.com/media/posts/3/responsive/selected-view-sm.webp 768w ,https://atlancia.com/media/posts/3/responsive/selected-view-md.webp 1024w ,https://atlancia.com/media/posts/3/responsive/selected-view-lg.webp 1366w ,https://atlancia.com/media/posts/3/responsive/selected-view-xl.webp 1600w ,https://atlancia.com/media/posts/3/responsive/selected-view-2xl.webp 1920w"></figure>
<p id="c94b" class="pw-post-body-paragraph vb vc qk ve b vf vg vh vi vj vk vl vm vn vo vp vq vr vs vt vu vv vw vx vy vz ga bk" data-selectable-paragraph="">To illustrate this point, let’s consider an abstract example. Imagine that there are three potential packages of work and one of them contains critical work. There’s no question that this work should take priority over all other work. However, if this critical work is bundled with other non-critical work, the entire package might be completed before other packages containing high-priority work. In this scenario, the lower-priority work ends up taking precedence simply because it was packaged together with the critical work. By breaking work down into smaller, more manageable pieces, teams can avoid this issue and ensure that the most important work always takes priority.</p>
<p id="7b72" class="pw-post-body-paragraph vb vc qk ve b vf vg vh vi vj vk vl vm vn vo vp vq vr vs vt vu vv vw vx vy vz ga bk" data-selectable-paragraph="">While on the subject of processes, another common pattern is historical linkage; rules and procedures that persist even if they are no longer relevant or useful. For example, some project methodologies require consultation with a vendor or asset management team as a precaution against licensing overages and legal risks. While this may have made sense in the past, with the rise of cloud technology, the need for such consultations is much lower (with software included in the service offering). However, because of the long-standing association between vendor management and licensing, this may be embedded as a required step for going live with delivery even though the previous risk has subsided.</p>
<h1 id="cdb9" class="wi wj qk bf wk lb wl lc le lf wm lg li in wn io ir ll wo lm lp lq wp lr lu wq bk" data-selectable-paragraph="">Idea 4: Who is being served?</h1>
<p id="1821" class="pw-post-body-paragraph vb vc qk ve b vf wr vh vi vj ws vl vm vn wt vp vq vr wu vt vu vv wv vx vy vz ga bk" data-selectable-paragraph="">Finally, and usually done in concert with the above ideas, is to look at “who is being served” by a choice.</p>
<p id="8c5b" class="pw-post-body-paragraph vb vc qk ve b vf vg vh vi vj vk vl vm vn vo vp vq vr vs vt vu vv vw vx vy vz ga bk" data-selectable-paragraph="">I recall years ago during the transition from an older platform for document management to a newer one, I was part of a group to decide what the folder structure ought to be for projects and support teams. The facilitator in the discussion walked in with the assumption that we needed to have the same structure for everyone. This assumption certainly made sense for their project, once defined it could be copied and pasted for everyone and they could move on. However, in representing teams’ needs the group had very different ideas of what worked best for them.</p>
<p id="0ffe" class="pw-post-body-paragraph vb vc qk ve b vf vg vh vi vj vk vl vm vn vo vp vq vr vs vt vu vv vw vx vy vz ga bk" data-selectable-paragraph="">Seeing an opportunity to ask, I posed a question to the group on where this assumption was made. The conversation went a little something like this:</p>
<p id="45b7" class="pw-post-body-paragraph vb vc qk ve b vf vg vh vi vj vk vl vm vn vo vp vq vr vs vt vu vv vw vx vy vz ga bk" data-selectable-paragraph=""><em class="vd">Facilitator: </em>“We need to standardize folder structure so that when a team member joins from another project they can find documents.”</p>
<p id="831d" class="pw-post-body-paragraph vb vc qk ve b vf vg vh vi vj vk vl vm vn vo vp vq vr vs vt vu vv vw vx vy vz ga bk" data-selectable-paragraph=""><em class="vd">Me: </em>“How often does it happen?”</p>
<p id="7173" class="pw-post-body-paragraph vb vc qk ve b vf vg vh vi vj vk vl vm vn vo vp vq vr vs vt vu vv vw vx vy vz ga bk" data-selectable-paragraph=""><em class="vd">Facilitator: </em>“Maybe a couple of times a year”</p>
<p id="9d3a" class="pw-post-body-paragraph vb vc qk ve b vf vg vh vi vj vk vl vm vn vo vp vq vr vs vt vu vv vw vx vy vz ga bk" data-selectable-paragraph=""><em class="vd">Me:</em> “Are we sure that designing a standard system to serve a twice-a-year event, over allowing the unique needs of teams and projects to be served is the best approach? When I’ve seen new team members join there’s usually been additional guidance provided, a “buddy system” usually, to help them orient themselves on what’s important. Wouldn’t that help serve that need?”</p>
<p id="9022" class="pw-post-body-paragraph vb vc qk ve b vf vg vh vi vj vk vl vm vn vo vp vq vr vs vt vu vv vw vx vy vz ga bk" data-selectable-paragraph="">Others seemed to react positively to the idea and the discussion following was more positive. There is no current standard, but there is a “starting” template to get teams off on the right foot. We struck a better balance.</p>
<p id="2bb8" class="pw-post-body-paragraph vb vc qk ve b vf vg vh vi vj vk vl vm vn vo vp vq vr vs vt vu vv vw vx vy vz ga bk" data-selectable-paragraph="">Another example was offered above, requests that may come for status reporting. It’s certainly understandable for leaders to want visibility into work. Yet, accepting that reporting doesn’t come for free and that when data on team performance “escapes” the team it costs the team safety to make changes — especially when an experiment might cause a temporary slowdown. Is it worth serving a leader’s need for observability over the potential drawbacks of lower team safety and less available time for work? Perhaps, but raising the discussion and balancing leadership’s need to work with their peers, stakeholders and other leaders allows for more nuance, especially for metrics that may influence team behaviours.</p>
<p id="4591" class="pw-post-body-paragraph vb vc qk ve b vf vg vh vi vj vk vl vm vn vo vp vq vr vs vt vu vv vw vx vy vz ga bk" data-selectable-paragraph="">The classic adage of <a class="ag xd" href="https://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/Goodhart%27s_law" rel="noopener ugc nofollow" target="_blank">Goodheart’s Law</a>: would state that “when a measure becomes a target, it ceases to be a good measure.” An unfortunate example of this has occurred in hospitals in the UK where a focus on individual mortality rates for surgeons alters their behaviour with <a class="ag xd" href="https://www.telegraph.co.uk/science/2016/06/03/one-in-three-heart-surgeons-refuse-difficult-operations-to-avoid/" rel="noopener ugc nofollow" target="_blank">1 in 3 surgeons reported avoiding difficult cases to protect their metrics</a>. The trade-off we make when metrics escape, doesn’t mean we ought to avoid reporting, but that we should discuss what effects might come from them.</p>
<p id="75ec" class="pw-post-body-paragraph vb vc qk ve b vf vg vh vi vj vk vl vm vn vo vp vq vr vs vt vu vv vw vx vy vz ga bk" data-selectable-paragraph="">For those in software, there are well-established metrics available, colloquially called the<a class="ag xd" href="https://cloud.google.com/blog/products/devops-sre/using-the-four-keys-to-measure-your-devops-performance" rel="noopener ugc nofollow" target="_blank"> DORA metrics</a>, with years of research behind them. These metrics are described by Google as:</p>
<p id="d3b4" class="pw-post-body-paragraph vb vc qk ve b vf vg vh vi vj vk vl vm vn vo vp vq vr vs vt vu vv vw vx vy vz ga bk" data-selectable-paragraph=""><em class="vd">Deployment Frequency — How often an organization successfully releases to production</em></p>
<p id="f113" class="pw-post-body-paragraph vb vc qk ve b vf vg vh vi vj vk vl vm vn vo vp vq vr vs vt vu vv vw vx vy vz ga bk" data-selectable-paragraph=""><em class="vd">Lead Time for Changes — The amount of time it takes a commit to get into production</em></p>
<p id="2ede" class="pw-post-body-paragraph vb vc qk ve b vf vg vh vi vj vk vl vm vn vo vp vq vr vs vt vu vv vw vx vy vz ga bk" data-selectable-paragraph=""><em class="vd">Change Failure Rate — The percentage of deployments causing a failure in production</em></p>
<p id="f1ff" class="pw-post-body-paragraph vb vc qk ve b vf vg vh vi vj vk vl vm vn vo vp vq vr vs vt vu vv vw vx vy vz ga bk" data-selectable-paragraph=""><em class="vd">Time to Restore Service — How long it takes an organization to recover from a failure in production</em></p>
<h1 id="f447" class="wi wj qk bf wk lb wl lc le lf wm lg li in wn io ir ll wo lm lp lq wp lr lu wq bk" data-selectable-paragraph="">Wrap-Up</h1>
<p id="85ad" class="pw-post-body-paragraph vb vc qk ve b vf wr vh vi vj ws vl vm vn wt vp vq vr wu vt vu vv wv vx vy vz ga bk" data-selectable-paragraph="">In environments where we are constantly making decisions, it’s easy to overlook the assumptions and trade-offs we make. The idea of a free lunch is a myth; everything we do comes at a cost. A trade-off mentality, informed by the four ideas above, has helped me have better conversations with others and better introspection. By acknowledging the constraints that underlie our systems, I feel better equipped to have constructive, open conversations.</p>
<p id="0f07" class="pw-post-body-paragraph vb vc qk ve b vf vg vh vi vj vk vl vm vn vo vp vq vr vs vt vu vv vw vx vy vz ga bk" data-selectable-paragraph="">While it’s been helpful for now to adopt a more inquisitive “trade-off mentality,” it’s still a work in progress. Through this lens, I work to support better dialogue. If you’re reading this, try it out the next time you are confronted with a difficult decision or hear a statement that “doesn’t sit right.” Remember to acknowledge that nothing comes for free and when we work in complex environments, we work best when we openly discuss our ideas and concerns. When you are brought into these discussions, challenge yourself to question “What’s the trade-off here?”</p>
            ]]>
        </content>
    </entry>
    <entry>
        <title>Changing Requirements to be a Successful Business Analyst</title>
        <author>
            <name>Liam Shaw</name>
        </author>
        <link href="https://atlancia.com/changing-requirements-to-be-a-successful-business-analyst.html"/>
        <id>https://atlancia.com/changing-requirements-to-be-a-successful-business-analyst.html</id>
        <media:content url="https://atlancia.com/media/posts/2/bapost.jpg" medium="image" />

        <updated>2019-06-14T00:00:00-04:00</updated>
            <summary>
                <![CDATA[
                        <img src="https://atlancia.com/media/posts/2/bapost.jpg" alt="" />
                    A look into personal experience with business analysis, agile and modern projects. My first exposure to the business analyst role was at the Canadian Food Inspection Agency (CFIA), while working with a team focused on policy. While there, I was fortunate enough to involve myself&hellip;
                ]]>
            </summary>
        <content type="html">
            <![CDATA[
                    <p><img src="https://atlancia.com/media/posts/2/bapost.jpg" class="type:primaryImage" alt="" /></p>
                <p id="751b" class="pw-post-body-paragraph mv mw ho mx b my mz na nb nc nd ne nf ng nh ni nj nk nl nm nn no np nq nr ns gp bk" data-selectable-paragraph=""><em class="nt">A look into personal experience with business analysis, agile and modern projects.</em></p>
<p id="7b5b" class="pw-post-body-paragraph mv mw ho mx b my mz na nb nc nd ne nf ng nh ni nj nk nl nm nn no np nq nr ns gp bk" data-selectable-paragraph="">My first exposure to the business analyst role was at the Canadian Food Inspection Agency (CFIA), while working with a team focused on policy. While there, I was fortunate enough to involve myself in other initiatives, giving me exposure to a new world of roles within the organization.</p>
<p id="259b" class="pw-post-body-paragraph mv mw ho mx b my mz na nb nc nd ne nf ng nh ni nj nk nl nm nn no np nq nr ns gp bk" data-selectable-paragraph="">After being asked to help out in coordinating some projects I began work with the corporate planning office. The first meeting we had I was introduced to a role new to me, called a <em class="nt">business analyst (BA).</em></p>
<p id="d16d" class="pw-post-body-paragraph mv mw ho mx b my mz na nb nc nd ne nf ng nh ni nj nk nl nm nn no np nq nr ns gp bk" data-selectable-paragraph="">Meeting this team of BAs, I felt a real connection to the role, that I could have a career in front of me. There was a real professional practice to what I felt was natural, but was ultimately novel in a policy world. That when working on an initiative we should have a clear vision for why we were doing it, what we hoped to resolve, and what success would look like. Business analysis offered a repeatable methodology for obtaining these answers.</p>
<p id="800e" class="pw-post-body-paragraph mv mw ho mx b my mz na nb nc nd ne nf ng nh ni nj nk nl nm nn no np nq nr ns gp bk" data-selectable-paragraph="">The next initiative I began was towards the development of a standard operating procedures guide to navigate the Agency’s corporate policies and procedures. Throughout this work, there were innumerable “whys” I wanted to ask to bring context to the instructions. I felt drawn to provide background when expecting users to follow instructions. Context, I felt, was key in getting buy-in.</p>
<p id="63f1" class="pw-post-body-paragraph mv mw ho mx b my mz na nb nc nd ne nf ng nh ni nj nk nl nm nn no np nq nr ns gp bk" data-selectable-paragraph="">Always questioning the “why” behind a seemingly infinite abyss of process, I was particularly drawn to the process re-engineering elements of the task. I began to look for support from professional disciplines to my incessant probing. My research revealed that again, business analysis would help me apply some method my instincts.</p>
<p id="7dff" class="pw-post-body-paragraph mv mw ho mx b my mz na nb nc nd ne nf ng nh ni nj nk nl nm nn no np nq nr ns gp bk" data-selectable-paragraph="">Learning this, I sought to attain more formal education, leading me to sign up for a program offered jointly by Carleton and York Universities’ business schools. At this program I had the good fortune to learn from some early members in the founding of the International Institute of Business Analysis (IIBA) and some of the world’s first official <em class="nt">Business Analysts.</em></p>
<p id="7676" class="pw-post-body-paragraph mv mw ho mx b my mz na nb nc nd ne nf ng nh ni nj nk nl nm nn no np nq nr ns gp bk" data-selectable-paragraph="">They shared with the class that the reason they founded the IIBA and created the role was to support a clear value proposition: projects frequently fail and the most frequent cause was poor management of requirements. A role that directly addressed this problem would have a strong return on investment.</p>
<p id="9951" class="pw-post-body-paragraph mv mw ho mx b my mz na nb nc nd ne nf ng nh ni nj nk nl nm nn no np nq nr ns gp bk" data-selectable-paragraph="">While in the formative years of the role, there were debates on title and responsibilities. Before settling on <em class="nt">Business Analyst</em>, a leading candidate was “Requirements Manager.” Along with the title the role would exist on par with the Project Manager, taking accountability for the scope of an initiative. When incomplete and changing requirements were showing up among the top <a class="ag nu" href="https://www.csus.edu/indiv/r/rengstorffj/obe152-spring02/articles/standishchaos.pdf" rel="noopener ugc nofollow" target="_blank">reasons for project failures,</a> the case was clear: managing requirements would reduce the risk of project failures and save millions in sunk costs.</p>
<p id="7128" class="pw-post-body-paragraph mv mw ho mx b my mz na nb nc nd ne nf ng nh ni nj nk nl nm nn no np nq nr ns gp bk" data-selectable-paragraph="">This concept of formally managed “requirements” was new to me. They weren’t what had drawn me to the role, nor were they what the business analysts I first met were focused on. The work that the BAs were doing that drew me to the profession was much more focused on identifying the value to the organization and managing to fit it back in as development progressed.</p>
<h1 id="90e6" class="nv nw ho bf nx ny nz oa ob oc od oe of og oh oi oj ok ol om on oo op oq or os bk" data-selectable-paragraph="">What do I need to be successful?</h1>
<p id="e3d3" class="pw-post-body-paragraph mv mw ho mx b my ot na nb nc ou ne nf ng ov ni nj nk ow nm nn no ox nq nr ns gp bk" data-selectable-paragraph="">Requirements in the traditional sense simply help define what an initiative needs to achieve to be successful. But there are a few issues with the concept:</p>
<ul class="">
<li id="fe4e" class="mv mw ho mx b my mz na nb nc nd ne nf ng nh ni nj nk nl nm nn no np nq nr ns oy oz pa bk" data-selectable-paragraph="">They capture the best knowledge available <strong class="mx hp">at a point in time</strong> and rarely change; even worse they often reflect the best understanding of technology by non-technical users without having seen a system or prototype</li>
<li id="1b72" class="mv mw ho mx b my pb na nb nc pc ne nf ng pd ni nj nk pe nm nn no pf nq nr ns oy oz pa bk" data-selectable-paragraph="">They apply formality to what often would be better served as a conversation or dialogue</li>
<li id="405c" class="mv mw ho mx b my pb na nb nc pc ne nf ng pd ni nj nk pe nm nn no pf nq nr ns oy oz pa bk" data-selectable-paragraph="">By investing time in documenting them and going through approvals, there is a sunk cost that makes it difficult to change</li>
<li id="7174" class="mv mw ho mx b my pb na nb nc pc ne nf ng pd ni nj nk pe nm nn no pf nq nr ns oy oz pa bk" data-selectable-paragraph="">There is often resistance to changing them through existing project mechanisms, such as change control, even when new information is uncovered</li>
</ul>
<p id="c34d" class="pw-post-body-paragraph mv mw ho mx b my mz na nb nc nd ne nf ng nh ni nj nk nl nm nn no np nq nr ns gp bk" data-selectable-paragraph="">These issues are similar to those that hamper the growth of the business analysis practice. The best knowledge available when the role was being created was that the majority of software development was occurring through projects, those projects were failing at an alarming rate (nearly 1/3 being cancelled) and that poor management of requirements was a significant contributor.</p>
<p id="7701" class="pw-post-body-paragraph mv mw ho mx b my mz na nb nc nd ne nf ng nh ni nj nk nl nm nn no np nq nr ns gp bk" data-selectable-paragraph="">However, today, less than 20% of projects are cancelled and an increasingly large number of projects are being done in an Agile manner (in which only <a class="ag nu" href="https://www.standishgroup.com/sample_research_files/CHAOSReport2015-Final.pdf" rel="noopener ugc nofollow" target="_blank">9% of projects</a> fail). In the most common Agile methodology, Scrum, there is no specific Business Analyst role. The wild west of projects looks to be maturing, finding new ways to be successful without the tools of projects past.</p>
<p id="f9de" class="pw-post-body-paragraph mv mw ho mx b my mz na nb nc nd ne nf ng nh ni nj nk nl nm nn no np nq nr ns gp bk" data-selectable-paragraph="">What this tells us is a story of a core skill-set that is languishing, yet the role is growing:</p>
<figure class="ph pi pj pk pl gy gu gv paragraph-image">
<div class="gz ha fl hb bh hc" tabindex="0" role="button"><span class="fu hd he an hf hg hh hi hj speechify-ignore">Zoom image will be displayed</span>
<div class="gu gv pg"><figure class="bh hk hl c"><source srcset="https://miro.medium.com/v2/resize:fit:640/format:webp/1*_Owzsgi04QRQMBjp5Y8uzA.png 640w, https://miro.medium.com/v2/resize:fit:720/format:webp/1*_Owzsgi04QRQMBjp5Y8uzA.png 720w, https://miro.medium.com/v2/resize:fit:750/format:webp/1*_Owzsgi04QRQMBjp5Y8uzA.png 750w, https://miro.medium.com/v2/resize:fit:786/format:webp/1*_Owzsgi04QRQMBjp5Y8uzA.png 786w, https://miro.medium.com/v2/resize:fit:828/format:webp/1*_Owzsgi04QRQMBjp5Y8uzA.png 828w, https://miro.medium.com/v2/resize:fit:1100/format:webp/1*_Owzsgi04QRQMBjp5Y8uzA.png 1100w, https://miro.medium.com/v2/resize:fit:1400/format:webp/1*_Owzsgi04QRQMBjp5Y8uzA.png 1400w" sizes="(min-resolution: 4dppx) and (max-width: 700px) 50vw, (-webkit-min-device-pixel-ratio: 4) and (max-width: 700px) 50vw, (min-resolution: 3dppx) and (max-width: 700px) 67vw, (-webkit-min-device-pixel-ratio: 3) and (max-width: 700px) 65vw, (min-resolution: 2.5dppx) and (max-width: 700px) 80vw, (-webkit-min-device-pixel-ratio: 2.5) and (max-width: 700px) 80vw, (min-resolution: 2dppx) and (max-width: 700px) 100vw, (-webkit-min-device-pixel-ratio: 2) and (max-width: 700px) 100vw, 700px" type="image/webp"><source data-testid="og" srcset="https://miro.medium.com/v2/resize:fit:640/1*_Owzsgi04QRQMBjp5Y8uzA.png 640w, https://miro.medium.com/v2/resize:fit:720/1*_Owzsgi04QRQMBjp5Y8uzA.png 720w, https://miro.medium.com/v2/resize:fit:750/1*_Owzsgi04QRQMBjp5Y8uzA.png 750w, https://miro.medium.com/v2/resize:fit:786/1*_Owzsgi04QRQMBjp5Y8uzA.png 786w, https://miro.medium.com/v2/resize:fit:828/1*_Owzsgi04QRQMBjp5Y8uzA.png 828w, https://miro.medium.com/v2/resize:fit:1100/1*_Owzsgi04QRQMBjp5Y8uzA.png 1100w, https://miro.medium.com/v2/resize:fit:1400/1*_Owzsgi04QRQMBjp5Y8uzA.png 1400w" sizes="(min-resolution: 4dppx) and (max-width: 700px) 50vw, (-webkit-min-device-pixel-ratio: 4) and (max-width: 700px) 50vw, (min-resolution: 3dppx) and (max-width: 700px) 67vw, (-webkit-min-device-pixel-ratio: 3) and (max-width: 700px) 65vw, (min-resolution: 2.5dppx) and (max-width: 700px) 80vw, (-webkit-min-device-pixel-ratio: 2.5) and (max-width: 700px) 80vw, (min-resolution: 2dppx) and (max-width: 700px) 100vw, (-webkit-min-device-pixel-ratio: 2) and (max-width: 700px) 100vw, 700px"><img  role="presentation" src="https://miro.medium.com/v2/resize:fit:875/1*_Owzsgi04QRQMBjp5Y8uzA.png" alt="" width="700" height="344" loading="lazy" data-is-external-image="true"></figure></picture></div>
</div>
</figure>
<h1 id="78d6" class="nv nw ho bf nx ny nz oa ob oc od oe of og oh oi oj ok ol om on oo op oq or os bk" data-selectable-paragraph="">What makes us successful?</h1>
<p id="8215" class="pw-post-body-paragraph mv mw ho mx b my ot na nb nc ou ne nf ng ov ni nj nk ow nm nn no ox nq nr ns gp bk" data-selectable-paragraph="">The role of the business analyst has become increasingly common in organizations and looking to grow (in the US an <a class="ag nu" href="https://www.floridatechonline.com/blog/business/business-analyst-career-and-salary-profile/" rel="noopener ugc nofollow" target="_blank">expected 14% growth</a> from 2014 to 2024). What are they doing if they aren’t focused on what we used to call “business analysis?”</p>
<p id="c0b0" class="pw-post-body-paragraph mv mw ho mx b my mz na nb nc nd ne nf ng nh ni nj nk nl nm nn no np nq nr ns gp bk" data-selectable-paragraph="">From personal experience, I have seen a shift from when I started working as a Business Analyst in 2011. When I began, I was working on one of the last major initiatives managed with strict requirements traceability, focused on stringent use cases and detailed requirements. Artifacts that feel like relics today.</p>
<p id="dcee" class="pw-post-body-paragraph mv mw ho mx b my mz na nb nc nd ne nf ng nh ni nj nk nl nm nn no np nq nr ns gp bk" data-selectable-paragraph="">Throughout the project, I never felt the like the work I did was really adding value to the end users. Instead it felt more akin to writing a dictionary, something that would never be read as a whole but referenced if we encountered a word we didn’t understand. This wasn’t valuable to the people who needed a new system to do their jobs. Sure it was <em class="nt">potentially</em> valuable to investment governance, audit and project management if something went wrong. But choosing to focus on potential value for potential stakeholders over real users was foolhardy.</p>
<p id="ce3c" class="pw-post-body-paragraph mv mw ho mx b my mz na nb nc nd ne nf ng nh ni nj nk nl nm nn no np nq nr ns gp bk" data-selectable-paragraph="">The core focus of my work was to reduce the drift of the project from an objective set at a point with the least information in the project life-cycle. Even worse, to produce work that would make course correction more costly.</p>
<p id="ba9b" class="pw-post-body-paragraph mv mw ho mx b my mz na nb nc nd ne nf ng nh ni nj nk nl nm nn no np nq nr ns gp bk" data-selectable-paragraph="">What felt the most valuable was not the work I was supposed to be focused on. Instead, I found that the most rewarding work fit into two areas; ensuring that the project “fit” into the organization and leveraging soft skills like facilitation and consensus building to connect the many parties involved and help them understand the complexities behind decisions.</p>
<figure class="ph pi pj pk pl gy gu gv paragraph-image">
<div class="gz ha fl hb bh hc" tabindex="0" role="button"><span class="fu hd he an hf hg hh hi hj speechify-ignore">Zoom image will be displayed</span>
<div class="gu gv pm"><figure class="bh hk hl c"><source srcset="https://miro.medium.com/v2/resize:fit:640/format:webp/1*n9cRtQ9iMSr9AYwRvP6RuA.png 640w, https://miro.medium.com/v2/resize:fit:720/format:webp/1*n9cRtQ9iMSr9AYwRvP6RuA.png 720w, https://miro.medium.com/v2/resize:fit:750/format:webp/1*n9cRtQ9iMSr9AYwRvP6RuA.png 750w, https://miro.medium.com/v2/resize:fit:786/format:webp/1*n9cRtQ9iMSr9AYwRvP6RuA.png 786w, https://miro.medium.com/v2/resize:fit:828/format:webp/1*n9cRtQ9iMSr9AYwRvP6RuA.png 828w, https://miro.medium.com/v2/resize:fit:1100/format:webp/1*n9cRtQ9iMSr9AYwRvP6RuA.png 1100w, https://miro.medium.com/v2/resize:fit:1400/format:webp/1*n9cRtQ9iMSr9AYwRvP6RuA.png 1400w" sizes="(min-resolution: 4dppx) and (max-width: 700px) 50vw, (-webkit-min-device-pixel-ratio: 4) and (max-width: 700px) 50vw, (min-resolution: 3dppx) and (max-width: 700px) 67vw, (-webkit-min-device-pixel-ratio: 3) and (max-width: 700px) 65vw, (min-resolution: 2.5dppx) and (max-width: 700px) 80vw, (-webkit-min-device-pixel-ratio: 2.5) and (max-width: 700px) 80vw, (min-resolution: 2dppx) and (max-width: 700px) 100vw, (-webkit-min-device-pixel-ratio: 2) and (max-width: 700px) 100vw, 700px" type="image/webp"><source data-testid="og" srcset="https://miro.medium.com/v2/resize:fit:640/1*n9cRtQ9iMSr9AYwRvP6RuA.png 640w, https://miro.medium.com/v2/resize:fit:720/1*n9cRtQ9iMSr9AYwRvP6RuA.png 720w, https://miro.medium.com/v2/resize:fit:750/1*n9cRtQ9iMSr9AYwRvP6RuA.png 750w, https://miro.medium.com/v2/resize:fit:786/1*n9cRtQ9iMSr9AYwRvP6RuA.png 786w, https://miro.medium.com/v2/resize:fit:828/1*n9cRtQ9iMSr9AYwRvP6RuA.png 828w, https://miro.medium.com/v2/resize:fit:1100/1*n9cRtQ9iMSr9AYwRvP6RuA.png 1100w, https://miro.medium.com/v2/resize:fit:1400/1*n9cRtQ9iMSr9AYwRvP6RuA.png 1400w" sizes="(min-resolution: 4dppx) and (max-width: 700px) 50vw, (-webkit-min-device-pixel-ratio: 4) and (max-width: 700px) 50vw, (min-resolution: 3dppx) and (max-width: 700px) 67vw, (-webkit-min-device-pixel-ratio: 3) and (max-width: 700px) 65vw, (min-resolution: 2.5dppx) and (max-width: 700px) 80vw, (-webkit-min-device-pixel-ratio: 2.5) and (max-width: 700px) 80vw, (min-resolution: 2dppx) and (max-width: 700px) 100vw, (-webkit-min-device-pixel-ratio: 2) and (max-width: 700px) 100vw, 700px"><img  role="presentation" src="https://miro.medium.com/v2/resize:fit:875/1*n9cRtQ9iMSr9AYwRvP6RuA.png" alt="" width="700" height="447" loading="lazy" data-is-external-image="true"></figure></picture></div>
</div>
</figure>
<p id="7594" class="pw-post-body-paragraph mv mw ho mx b my mz na nb nc nd ne nf ng nh ni nj nk nl nm nn no np nq nr ns gp bk" data-selectable-paragraph="">Managing requirements in the traditional methodologies only added complexity. I distinctly remember looking at project with 500+ discrete requirements and thinking to myself; “how can anybody possibly be sure these are still true?” The “modern” Business Analyst has value, and is most valuable when they are contributing their skill-set to work that helps the organization navigate itself through the endless sea of change on the horizon.</p>
<p id="1480" class="pw-post-body-paragraph mv mw ho mx b my mz na nb nc nd ne nf ng nh ni nj nk nl nm nn no np nq nr ns gp bk" data-selectable-paragraph="">The role of Business Analyst has a lot to contribute, but it’s most valuable when we can balance the interests of a project with the interests of the organization. In finding that balance, the role of Business Analyst returns to a clear value proposition. To do what the role has historically done well at, provide the organization an interface to support changes inside and out.</p>
<p id="5e95" class="pw-post-body-paragraph mv mw ho mx b my mz na nb nc nd ne nf ng nh ni nj nk nl nm nn no np nq nr ns gp bk" data-selectable-paragraph="">Business analysis as a practice dedicated to managing requirements is on its way out. However, business analysis has a much brighter future if it can address the complexity of systems, organizations, and their use of technology. It can also take the soft skills that have always been core to successfully managing requirements — e.g. consensus building, facilitation and negotiation — to modern development practices.</p>
            ]]>
        </content>
    </entry>
</feed>
